<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact relation of the siege before Yorke: of the taking of the suburbs, and of the approaches made within 40. yards of the walls: of the taking of the Kings mannor house there: and how the associated forces of Essex, Suffolk, &amp;c. under the Earle of Manchester, have severall times repulsed the enemy, and preserved some part of the suburbs from being consumed with fire. As it is sent in severall letters, dated at the Leaguer before York, the 6. and 7. of June. Published by Authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E50_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23535</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872031</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E50[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact relation of the siege before Yorke: of the taking of the suburbs, and of the approaches made within 40. yards of the walls: of the taking of the Kings mannor house there: and how the associated forces of Essex, Suffolk, &amp;c. under the Earle of Manchester, have severall times repulsed the enemy, and preserved some part of the suburbs from being consumed with fire. As it is sent in severall letters, dated at the Leaguer before York, the 6. and 7. of June. Published by Authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>June 12. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>York (England) --  History --  Siege, 1644 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Exact RELATION Of the Siege before YORKE: Of the taking of the Suburbs, and of the Approaches made within 40. yards of the Walls: Of the taking of the Kings Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor houſe there: And how the Aſſociated forces of <hi>Eſſex, Suffolk,</hi> &amp;c. under the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> have ſeverall times repulſed the Enemy, and preſerved ſome part of the Suburbs from being conſumed with fire.</p>
            <p>As it is ſent in ſeverall Letters, dated at the Leaguer before <hi>York,</hi> the 6. and 7. of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>London Printed for <hi>R. White.</hi> June 12. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:155167:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155167:2"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Leaguer before <hi>York,</hi> 
               <date>the ſixth of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1644.</date>
            </head>
            <p>SInce my laſt by the Poſt the 30. of <hi>May</hi> laſt, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> hath taken <hi>Bolton</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> wherein there were a thouſand five hundred Club-men, and Colonell <hi>Rigby</hi> with 2000. Armed men drawne from the Siege of <hi>Latham,</hi> Colonell <hi>Rigby</hi> himſelfe who is come hither faith that he loſt there five bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells of Powder, two Drakes, and other Ammunition, and not 200. men in all kild, moſt of the reſt ſaving themſelves by flight; but he conceives he loſt neere 500. Armes, the vulgar report gives the loſſe to be greater; howſoever he is now about to rally his ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered men, and hopes to get them ſhortly together. Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> forces range over a great part of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> but his principall quarter is at <hi>VViggon,</hi> and to that Towne he drawes the forces raiſed by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Array: His Army increaſes by the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of the Earle of <hi>Darby,</hi> and the Popiſh Gentry there, that do all flock to him, and by the addition of Generall <hi>Gorings</hi> forces, who came to him on <hi>Monday</hi> laſt at <hi>Berry;</hi> and then it was alſo believed, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended preſently to come to <hi>York</hi> to raiſe the Siege: But this day the 6. of <hi>June,</hi> Sir <hi>John Meldrum,</hi> writes that he conceives his forces not to exceed ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, and that they bend Southwards, as he thinkes, to take <hi>VVarington,</hi> and <hi>Leverpoole:</hi> but it is thought he will march to meet the King, if he once paſſe South out of <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155167:3"/>
            <p> This day alſo Letters were intercepted from Sir <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Muſgrave</hi> to Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> whereby I perceive <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi> hath ſent for him, and all his forces of <hi>VVeſtmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Cumberland;</hi> which Sir <hi>Philip</hi> promiſeth to performe, but not ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> there are Garriſons of good ſtrength, in <hi>VVarington, Leverpoole,</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> and an Army of ſeven or 8000. Armed men in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> where Sir <hi>John Meldrum</hi> reſides, and hath the command of all the Country; and the Parliaments ſhips lately come to <hi>Lever poole</hi> do much encourage the Souldiers there; ſo that I do not give <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> for loſt, though I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Rupert</hi> will pillage the Country ſore, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his Army; neither of which can be prevented without a greater inconvenience.</p>
            <p>From Biſhoprick we hear that all the forces of the enemy are retreated into <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> (the Troops of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</hi> excepted, that continue yet at <hi>Durham</hi>) which gives ſome aſſurance of the publique report of the Lord <hi>Calendars</hi> being at <hi>Alnewick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third of <hi>June</hi> our forces tooke <hi>VValton</hi>-hall neer <hi>VVakefield,</hi> and in it Sir <hi>Francis VVortley,</hi> the elder, the firſt incendiarie in this County, that publikely engaged a party for the King againſt the Parliament, and 120. ſouldiers with him, who yeilded themſelves priſoners after they had kild ſeverall of our men.</p>
            <p>And third of <hi>June</hi> in the night, 60. horſe ſent by Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> from <hi>Scarbrough</hi> came to <hi>Buttercoms,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Henry Darley</hi> lodged; and the Draw-bridge being accidentally let down that night, they entred, and took him in bed, and carried him priſoner to Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155167:3"/>
            <p> On <hi>Monday</hi> the third of <hi>June</hi> the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> drew to the Leaguer at <hi>Yorke,</hi> about 6000. foot and a thouſand horſe, and twelve field pieces, and his men are quartered before <hi>Bowdom</hi> barre, and that ſide to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Clifton,</hi> they are very brave ſouldiers, and every day fall upon ſome part, and beat the enemy.</p>
            <p>And now having theſe forces added to our other Armies, the enemy is ſhut up far cloſer then before: and the Generals conſult how the work may be made ſhort with leaſt loſſe of their men: and yeſternight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>June</hi> the fifth, they have cauſed a work to be raiſed for a battery, upon a hill neer Walm-gate, where there are four pieces of battery already planted, that have played all this afternoone upon the Caſtle, Tower, and Towne; and they from the Town have ſent us at leaſt an hundred Bullets from ſeverall Platformes in the Towne, but they have done us very little hurt, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one man killed, and what execution our Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance do in the City we cannot yet tell; But we are getting more pieces up to our new worke, which we know hath already put them into a very great fear, for this day they have fired moſt part of the Suburbs, and drawne their people into the Town; our men fall into the Suburbs and beat them in when they Sally our either to fire houſes or fetch in goods; but whileſt they skirmiſh the fire conſumes the houſes, they wil not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our men to quench it, for if the houſes could have been ſaved they would have been a great ſhelter for our men in their approaches.</p>
            <p>And the Suburb without Bowdom, where there were many faire houſes, being fired, the E. of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> men nevertheleſſe entred, and beat in the enemy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155167:4"/>this morning, and have ſaved much of the houſes from the fire, and doe gallery through them cloſe to the walls, ſo that it is to be hoped, that unleſſe ſuccours come ſpeedily to them, the Town will be taken or yielded. And to prevent Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> comming, the moſt part of our horſe and dragooneers are laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> who if they be not able to beat him back, yet will at leaſt ſtop his march untill theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be drawne up to them, and then they will, being all together, be able to fight with all the forces the King hath on the north ſide of Trent, if God give his bleſſing, which we all pray for.</p>
            <p>There is a bridge made of boats over the Owſe in <hi>Cliftonings,</hi> that the Armies may on a ſudden ſend ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour one to another.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>June,</hi> the Scots forces fetched a great many cattell and horſes from the enemy neer Micle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate barre, and kild many both horſe and foot of the enemy, I heare they left four and thirty dead, and brought away thirty priſoners, but all ſore wounded.</p>
            <p>And yeſterday <hi>June</hi> the 5. the Earle of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> men fell on neere <hi>VValm</hi>-gate, and took Saint <hi>Nicholas</hi> Church; but diſſerted it againe when they had gotten away eighty head of cattell from the enemy: and there is no day paſſeth but ſomething is done worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, for our men are full of courage, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to fall upon the Town whenſoever the Generalls thinke it fit to command them: <hi>Sandall</hi> Caſtle neere <hi>VVakefield</hi> was ſurrendred yeſterday.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iune the ſixth, 1644.</date> Leaguer before York.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155167:4"/>
            <head>Another Letter from the Leaguer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>York,</hi> 
               <date>
                  <hi>Iune</hi> 7. eleven a Clock at noon.</date>
            </head>
            <p>EVery day produces novelties, at preſent thus, Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> night laſt, was a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery made at the Windmil betwixt <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Leſlington,</hi> about eight ſcore diſtant from the Walls, and five piece of great Ordnance yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day placed in it, and divers ſhots made into the City, which have made viſible batteries, both in the Walls, Cliffords Tower, and other houſes, another battery was yeſterday got at S. <hi>Laurence</hi> Church, made within the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard next Wombgate, about fifty yards from the gate, and here, and in the Church, and houſes, there are about 3000. of our men.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Eglington</hi> with 4000. Scots, yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day entred, Gilligate, Marygate, and Mary Tower, &amp; have made a paſſage into the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor under ground: This laſt night a ſtrong pary ſallyed out of the City, and fell upon his men to beat them back, but could not prevaile, for 7000. of my Lo: <hi>Mancheſters,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Fairfaxes</hi> men fell into Wombgate, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the enemy, and had a ſore fight with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155167:5"/>them, the loſſe hitherto, I have not heard on either ſide: The Lo: Generall <hi>Leven</hi> with his Regiment fell upon a ſtrong Fort this laſt night, upon a hill, about eight ſcore diſtant from Skeldergate poſterne, and have taken it, and 120. men in it, whereof about 35. are brought in priſoners, the reſt killed, hee loſt ſome men in that ſervice; and in this Fort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very conſiderable, my Lo: intends to make a battery, and ſo from thence make ſhots at pleaſure into Town, and I do believe to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or the next day, they will Summon the City once more, and if not yeelded, then they may take the laſt farewell, for the Soldiers are mightily inraged, and I doubt will not be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to diſtinguiſh perſons: All this laſt night I ſaw great fires in three ſeverall places of the City, much of the Suburbs was burned before, except ſuch as our men have ſaved, and wee heare the enemy reſolve to burn the City, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then yeeld it, wee do hourely expect the iſſue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>York</hi> Leaguer, <date>7. of <hi>June,</hi> at eleven a Clock at noon.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
